Guide to the Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church Records, 1804-1997 AIS.1977.19
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church Records
1804-1997
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mt. Lebanon United Presbyterian Church (Mount Lebanon, Pa.)
AIS.1977.19
12 microfilm_reels
This church, first formed in 1804 as the Associate Reformed Congregation of Saw Mill Run, became Mt. Lebanon United Presbyterian in 1912. Shortly thereafter, the church was renamed the Mt. Lebanon United Presbyterian Church. The records cover the period 1804-1997.
History
The church, first formed in 1804 as the Associate Reformed Congregation of Saw Mill Run, comprised the united congregations of St. Clair and Mifflin. Most members were of Scotch-Irish heritage. In 1806, the first house of worship was built on Scott Road in what was then St. Clair Township. Around 1860, the name was changed to the St. Clair United Presbyterian Church. Minutes were not kept until 1843.
Mt. Lebanon came into legal existence in 1912. Shortly thereafter, the church was renamed the Mt. Lebanon United Presbyterian Church. In 1929 a new church, modeled after York Cathedral with its twin towers, was built. Since the 1930's many social and community programs have been added to the church's activities.
Scope and Content Notes
Records extend from 1804-1997 and includes session minutes; church registers; historical materials; sesquicentennial book, 1804-1954; trustees, congregational, and misc. minutes; cemetery records; called to colors cards, World War II, and financial records.
Records were filmed in segments as 77:19, 77:19a, 77:19b, and 98:17. The finding aid includes the exact microfilm reel to locate specific contents.
Note reels 9-12 (1968-1997) were added to this collection from AIS.1998.17 in November 2003. These records may overlap some of the earlier records.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Microfilmed by the Archives Service Center from originals in the possession of Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church, June 1977 and June 1998.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original records retained by Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church.
Previous Citation
Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church Records, 1804-1997, AIS.1977.19, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Mount Lebanon United Presbyterian Church, Records, 1804-1997, AIS 77:19, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh
Mount Lebanon (Pa.) -- Church history; Churches and Synagogues; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Presbyterian Church; Presbyterian Church -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- Church history; Church records and registers -- Pennsylvania -- Mount Lebanon; Mt. Lebanon United Presbyterian Church (Mount Lebanon, Pa.)
- Historical materials for the Sesquicentennial Book, One Hundred and Fifty Years, 1804-1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
- Registers, Vol. 1, 1858-1902 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1, 8)
- Registers, Vol. 2, 1901-1924 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
- Registers, Vol. 3, 1924-1944 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
- Registers, Vol. 4, July 1944-Dec. 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
- Registers, Vol. 5, Jan. 1961-Dec. 1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- Registers, Vol. 6, Jan. 1977-June 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 1, April 2, 1841-April 10, 1876 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 2, May 12, 1876-June 26, 1910 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 1-2)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 3, Sept. 2, 1910-Dec. 9, 1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 4, Jan. 4, 1922-Dec. 11, 1927 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 5, Jan. 18, 1928-Dec. 10, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 6, Jan. 3, 1934-Mar. 31, 1939 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 7, Apr. 2, 1939-Mar. 29, 1942 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 2-3)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 8, Apr. 3, 1942-Mar. 29, 1944 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 3)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 9, Apr. 2, 1944-Dec. 2, 1951 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 3-4)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 10, Jan. 29, 1952-Dec. 9, 1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 11, 1957-1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 12, Jan. 12, 1960-Dec. 31, 1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- Session Minutes, Vol. 13, Jan. 17, 1966-June 5, 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- Trustees Meeting Minutes, Vol. 1, St. Clair Congregation, 1843-1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- Trustees Meeting Minutes, Vol. 2, Building Committee, 1871-1875 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- Trustees Meeting Minutes, Vol. 3, Trustees, 1897-1910 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- General Meeting Minutes, V. 4, 1952-1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- General Meeting Minutes, Vol. 5, Jan. 1962-Dec. 1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- General Meeting Minutes, Vol. 6, Jan. 1970-Dec. 1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
- Congregational Minutes, Vol. 1, Apr. 1950-Dec.1965 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 6-7)
- Congregational Minutes, Vol. 2, Jan. 1966-Jan 1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
- Congregational Minutes, Vol. 3, Jan. 1975-Jan 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
- Trustees' Data Book, Undated (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
- Cemetery Records, 1865-1935 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Provides plans and lot purchase agreement.
- Called to Colors Cards -- World War II, 1943-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
  Contains rank, name, address, date entered service, birth date, serial number, branch of service, and information on person.
- Historical Materials -- Stained Glass Windows, 1927-1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
- Deed to One-Half Pew, Aug. 25, 1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
- Cash Book Ledger, Vol. 1, 1921-1926 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
- Cash Book Ledger, Vol. 2, 1953-1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
- St. Clair Congregation, 1801-1901 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
  Contains miscellaneous papers which include reports, history, correspondence, advertisements, 1803-1874, and financial records, 1837-1901.
- Monongahela Presbytery, 1876-1898 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
  Contains contribution reports of churches.
- General Presbyterian Council, 1877 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
  Contains a "Public Reception of Delegates" announcement.
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1869, 1935 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
  Contains Allegheny County election returns for 1869 and Session Report, 1935.
- Meeting Meetings, 1968-1997 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 9-10)
  Contains Corporation Minutes, Session Minutes, Retirement Plane Minutes, and Joint Board Minutes.
- Register, Jan. 1977-Dec. 1997 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  Contains registers for the parish. Included are lists of Pastars, Student Assistants, Deacons, Elders, Trustees, Baptisms, Marriages, and Deaths. The Series also includes lists of active, inactive, and affiliate members.
- Minutes, July 29, 1979-1997 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 10-12)
  Contains Session Minutes, Ecclesiastical Meeting Minutes and Joint Board Meeting Minutes.
- Trustee Minutes, 1977-1996 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 2, Reel 12)